<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vaibhav&#39;s Personal Website</title>
    <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vaibhav&#39;s Personal Website</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How I Built My Personal Website Using GitHub Pages and Cloudflare</title>
      <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/website/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/website/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Building my personal website was both a rewarding and educational experience. It taught me the fundamentals of hosting, web performance, DNS management, and security, while also allowing me to create a platform to showcase my work. Using &lt;strong&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/strong&gt; for free and &lt;strong&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/strong&gt; for performance optimization and security, I successfully launched a professional online presence with minimal cost. In this post, I’ll walk through how I set up the site, the tools I used, and the lessons I learned along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I Crafted My Resume and Plan to Help Others Do the Same</title>
      <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/cv-builder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/cv-builder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Building a resume is more than just listing skills and experiences. It’s about &lt;strong&gt;telling your story&lt;/strong&gt;—reflecting not only where you’ve been but where you’re going. Over the years, I’ve developed an approach to crafting resumes that balance academic achievements, professional experiences, and leadership roles. Now, as the newly elected &lt;strong&gt;Professional Development Officer&lt;/strong&gt;, I’m excited to begin leading initiatives that will help others refine their resumes, identify their strengths, and position themselves for success.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building My First Web Application: Field Stations Map</title>
      <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/web-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/web-app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Building my first web application, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vkulk094/FieldStationsMap&#34;&gt;FieldStationsMap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, was an incredible learning experience that introduced me to web development, cloud-based services, and Google&amp;rsquo;s mapping technologies. With the help of &lt;strong&gt;Google Maps API&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Google Cloud Console&lt;/strong&gt;, I created an interactive web app that visualizes field stations on a dynamic map. Over time, I also made significant quality-of-life improvements to enhance the application’s functionality and usability.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;concept-and-purpose&#34;&gt;Concept and Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;FieldStationsMap&lt;/strong&gt; project aims to visualize the locations of various field stations on an interactive map. I wanted to create a tool that would make it easy to explore the geographic distribution of field stations, with a focus on both ease of use and performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned from Presenting at the Ottawa Biology Symposium</title>
      <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/ocib/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/ocib/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Presenting at the &lt;strong&gt;Ottawa Biology Symposium 2024&lt;/strong&gt; was one of the most rewarding and enlightening experiences in my academic journey. The symposium gathered experts and students from various biological fields, giving me the opportunity to showcase my research on histone modifications in goldfish under hypoxic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-balancing-research-and-presentation&#34;&gt;Preparation: Balancing Research and Presentation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the symposium date approached, I spent weeks balancing the completion of my research with preparing my presentation. The challenge was not only in summarizing months of research into a concise presentation but also in ensuring that the technical aspects of my project were accessible to a broader audience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Expanding Role of Bioinformatics in Modern Science</title>
      <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/bioinformatics-role/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/bioinformatics-role/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bioinformatics sits at the crossroads of biology, computer science, and data analysis, transforming how we understand and apply biological information. Initially propelled by the Human Genome Project, bioinformatics has expanded beyond genomics into fields like proteomics, systems biology, and drug discovery, revolutionizing both research and medicine.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-foundation-of-bioinformatics&#34;&gt;The Foundation of Bioinformatics&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bioinformatics involves the development of computational tools and techniques for understanding biological data. Genomic data analysis, for example, relies on algorithms to identify gene sequences, predict functions, and assess genetic variations that influence disease susceptibility. Beyond genomics, bioinformatics now plays a crucial role in analyzing proteins (proteomics), understanding metabolic pathways, and modeling complex cellular networks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
