<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Web Development on Vaibhav&#39;s Personal Website</title>
    <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/tags/web-development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Web Development on Vaibhav&#39;s Personal Website</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/tags/web-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How I Built My Personal Website Using GitHub Pages and Cloudflare</title>
      <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/website/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/website/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Building my personal website was both a rewarding and educational experience. It taught me the fundamentals of hosting, web performance, DNS management, and security, while also allowing me to create a platform to showcase my work. Using &lt;strong&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/strong&gt; for free and &lt;strong&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/strong&gt; for performance optimization and security, I successfully launched a professional online presence with minimal cost. In this post, I’ll walk through how I set up the site, the tools I used, and the lessons I learned along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building My First Web Application: Field Stations Map</title>
      <link>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/web-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaibhavkulkarni.bio/blogs/web-app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Building my first web application, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vkulk094/FieldStationsMap&#34;&gt;FieldStationsMap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, was an incredible learning experience that introduced me to web development, cloud-based services, and Google&amp;rsquo;s mapping technologies. With the help of &lt;strong&gt;Google Maps API&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Google Cloud Console&lt;/strong&gt;, I created an interactive web app that visualizes field stations on a dynamic map. Over time, I also made significant quality-of-life improvements to enhance the application’s functionality and usability.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;concept-and-purpose&#34;&gt;Concept and Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;FieldStationsMap&lt;/strong&gt; project aims to visualize the locations of various field stations on an interactive map. I wanted to create a tool that would make it easy to explore the geographic distribution of field stations, with a focus on both ease of use and performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
